<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Stuff that matters]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Stuff that matters]]></description>
        <link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link>
        <generator>The Grid</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 02:53:16 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="undefinedrss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The nature of money - Part 1: Money is a promise]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<article><h1>The nature of money - Part 1: Money is a promise</h1><p>In our current day society it seems like money is at the center of virtually everything. It’s hard to think of anythingwithout money being involved in some way or another. The news is full of stories of governments struggling to managetheir debts. People all over the world are struggling to make ends meet or in other words, to earn enough money tofeed and clothe themselves and have a decent roof over their heads. And then I’m not even mentioning education andhealth care.
And yet, there is enough food to feed the entire planet and there is enough space for everyone to live. So why arepeople struggling?
One path worthy of exploration is to follow the money. A lot of people have restricted access to the one resource thatopens almost all doors: money. Just imagine that tomorrow money would not be an issue in your life anymore. Imaginewalking out of the door in the morning without having to worry about your expenses for the day. Cup of coffee on theway to work? No problem. Going out for lunch to that nice restaurant that opened up around the corner? Done! Takingthat trip to Hawaii you were dreaming of? Just book it! What would you do if you were assured there was enough? Howwould your life look like? Would you be on a perpetual holiday? Would you still work? Would you do the same work orother work? Would you start studying again? How would your life look like?
Money is not ‘real’
Before we dig into this, let’s first explore what is meant by ‘real’.
Everything you can touch and hold can be considered to be real. Virtual reality may start blurring that boundary butlet’s stay with physical stuff in the ‘real world’ for now. So your cup of coffee, the laptop, smartphone or tablet you arereading this article on, your car, trees, oceans, … All these things are real.
Experiences are real. They are not tangible like physical matter is but when you go for a swim, get a hug, run into a wall,go bungie jumping, are congratulated on a job well done, … all of this ‘feels’ real. It can make you feel good or bad ormaybe it doesn’t have a real impact on your state of being. One thing is for sure, you can say it happened and thatmakes it real.
Services are real. When someone does a service for you, you are left with something that was not there before.They can be put into 3 categories.
	•	There are those that result in something physical. A cup of coffee, a clean car, a house, … These can all beproduced through someone, or a group of people, providing you a service.
	•	Others provide you with an experience. A massage, a guided tour through a new city, a workout session with aprofessional trainer, … All transport services could also be put in this category since they provide you with theexperience of the transport itself and the experience of arrival at your destination. The same goes for travelagencies that arrange your trip for you.
	•	The last category has overlaps with the previous one. This is where you learn something. This can be a new skillor expanding your knowledge and insights. It overlaps with the previous category because learning is also anexperience.
Money is not ‘real’. The bills are real as are the coins and that’s where it ends.
Imagine you would be locked up in a room with 10 trillion dollars. That’s a lot! There is one catch, you can not exit thatroom for a whole month. There is no one you can communicate with. There is no way you can spend any of that moneyon anything. It’s just you and the dollar bills. No water, no food, no clothes … for a whole month. The money, real as thebills are, would be worthless. You could burn it for warmth if you manage to light them. You can not eat it and you cannot drink it. You could say it gives you an experience but a stack of regular paper would probably do about the same.
Money is like a promise. Imagine I promise to get you food. Depending on how well you know me you would trust memore or less in actually delivering on my promise. As long as you do not hold the food in your hands my promise doesnot have a lot of value. It might give you hope of eliminating your hunger but the promise in itself does not do that. Forthat I need to show up with the food and hand it over to you. At that point the promise is turned into something of realvalue.
Money works the same way. It is a promise to value, to something real. You also need other people around you that arewilling to trust that promise. People that are willing to accept it in exchange for something you want or need. And forthat people need to believe that the promise can be cashed in. That belief is both volatile and localised.
The volatility depends on the perceived trustworthiness of the currency. This is reflected in the foreignexchange market. Bitcoin, with its strong fluctuations, is a prime example of just how volatile the perceived value of acurrency can be.
It is localised because, in general, people will only accept the currency that is used locally. If I were to show up and offeryou 1 million Indian Rupees to buy a brand new top of the line TV set there’s a good chance you will refuse because youare not familiar with that currency (unless you live in India of course). Your belief and trust in that currency is a lotlower than the belief and trust in your local currency. Exceptions exist in those countries where the perceivedtrustworthiness of the local currency is low. In those countries dollars and euros are usually readily accepted.
Now, money in itself is not bad. There is a big advantage to using it too. When the trust remains stable, it’s a safesubstitute for value you don’t need right away. Having a ton of potatoes today is not particularly handy because theywill go bad before you can eat them. Their trading value also depends on the freshness and whether there is enoughdemand. Money does not have the problem that it becomes stale or that it rots away. People will probably acceptit longer than they are willing to accept your current batch of potatoes.
Conclusion
So, money in itself has no value. It holds a promise to value though. As long as there is someone else willing to accept itin exchange for something real, something you can actually use, goods or a service, you’re good. For that to happen, theother person must be familiar with the currency and trust it enough to belief that it will keep its perceived value longenough to be traded in for something he/she can use later on. In other words, money is a promise to something youwant/need. And by accepting money in exchange for goods or a service you are betting on the money keeping itspromise.
If tomorrow the currency you have in the bank would suddenly devaluate it would be the equivalent of your moneybreaking its promise to deliver value to you.
In the end, money derives its usefulness from the agreement and/or belief by a group of people that a certain currencyholds a stable promise to value. That it can function as a placeholder for value later on. This is not limited to officialcurrencies backed by nations. There are lots of complementary currencies all over the world which are also used as asubstitute for real value. Most of these currencies are constructed differently from the national currencies. More onthat in later posts.
The important thing though is that we see it for what it is: a tool. A substitute for real value, a promise to get that realvalue. And that’s where things are going horribly wrong in our current day society.
How and why will be explained in part 2: The hidden costs.</p><img src="https://the-grid-user-content.s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/d6094c69-b06b-4bbb-a95c-b524605a3ea8.png"></article>]]></description>
            <link>undefinedthe-nature-of-money-part-1-money-is-a-promise/index.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">bb11d44f-82b6-443b-a12b-7eaa506ffc25</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 02:52:32 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>